<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Alex Gonzalez - linux</title><link href="https://alexgonzalezc.dev/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://alexgonzalezc.dev/feeds/linux.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://alexgonzalezc.dev/</id><updated>2019-12-08T22:50:00+01:00</updated><subtitle>Hey! I'm Alex, a developer focused on data engineering, machine learning, data science and visualization.</subtitle><entry><title>How I got started with Linux</title><link href="https://alexgonzalezc.dev/posts/linux-dev-env.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-12-08T22:50:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-12-08T22:50:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Alex Gonzalez</name></author><id>tag:alexgonzalezc.dev,2019-12-08:/posts/linux-dev-env.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;An overview of my Linux development&amp;nbsp;setup.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently got the itch of purchasing a new laptop for development and learning, so I took the chance on Black Friday and got myself a nice &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HP&lt;/span&gt; Stream 14. I am a long-time Windows user so I thought it would be a great opportunity to get started with Linux and set up a developer workstation while documenting the&amp;nbsp;process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Objectives&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted this machine to be equipped&amp;nbsp;for:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;data science and machine learning&amp;nbsp;investigation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;writing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;web and software development, mostly in&amp;nbsp;Python&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;indie game&amp;nbsp;development&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cloud&amp;nbsp;deployments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For that, I will be using tools like Visual Studio Code, Zsh (with Oh My Zsh), Godot and a nice terminal emulator like&amp;nbsp;Tilix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Linux&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I searched for a bit trying to decide which Linux flavor I would use. I tried Elementary &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OS&lt;/span&gt; and Ubuntu Budgie, but finally decided myself for the true and tested Ubuntu 18.04 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LTS&lt;/span&gt;, which grants support and maintenance for up to 5 years. After all, I just want to learn and have fun with this&amp;nbsp;laptop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first, I experienced some issues with the system. For example, the Wi-Fi adapter wasn&amp;#8217;t recognised by the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OS&lt;/span&gt;, so I had no internet connection. The Stream 14 doesn&amp;#8217;t have an Ethernet port, so that wasn&amp;#8217;t an option either. Finally I had to use my phone&amp;#8217;s connection through &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USB&lt;/span&gt; thethering so I could run the following&amp;nbsp;commands:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;sudo apt-get upgrade
sudo apt-get update
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This fixes any broken packages. After that, I was able to install Git and clone a repo with the drivers for my adapters. This got my connection ready to start the real setup. The details are probably specific to the factory settings on my laptop so I won&amp;#8217;t really go over them, but &lt;a href="https://alexgonzalezc.dev/pages/contact.html"&gt;let me know&lt;/a&gt; if you&amp;#8217;re stuck with a similar issue and I&amp;#8217;ll try to help&amp;nbsp;out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Coding&amp;nbsp;tools&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#8217;s my default editor and developer tool. I love the extensible and customizable design, and the many &lt;a href="https://alexgonzalezc.dev/posts/vs-code-ninja.html"&gt;productivity hacks&lt;/a&gt; you can take advantage&amp;nbsp;of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://gnunn1.github.io/tilix-web/"&gt;Tilix&lt;/a&gt; is an awesome terminal emulator with integrated multiplexing (like &lt;code&gt;tmux&lt;/code&gt;) and can speed up your workflow significantly if used properly.
I also like &lt;a href="https://hyper.is/"&gt;Hyper&lt;/a&gt; as it is very simple and&amp;nbsp;lightweight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I started dabbling in game development, Godot has been the most approachable engine I have encountered. I tried &lt;a href="https://phaser.io/"&gt;PhaserJS&lt;/a&gt; briefly but my JavaScript is not that polished and I find an engine to be more more hollistic in developmnet as opposed to a framework like&amp;nbsp;Phaser.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Programming&amp;nbsp;languages&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though Python comes installed in Linux distros by default, its package manager &lt;code&gt;pip&lt;/code&gt; wasn&amp;#8217;t available on my system. A swift &lt;code&gt;sudo apt-get install pip3&lt;/code&gt; took that problem away.
Take note of the &lt;code&gt;pip3&lt;/code&gt; part, which installs the module for Python&amp;nbsp;3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also installed &lt;a href="https://julialang.org/"&gt;Julia 1.3&lt;/a&gt; to run some benchmarks against Python and try my hand at some development with this growing&amp;nbsp;language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I added some other stuff, languages like &lt;a href="https://vlang.io/"&gt;V&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.lua.org/"&gt;Lua&lt;/a&gt; to have more options to play with. As you can see, I have installed many different languages so I can mix and match my learning and find the niche I am most comfortable in. Many advocate against a &amp;#8220;jack of all trades&amp;#8221; approach, but I find breadth of knowledge more useful than depth in general situations. You can always specialise if&amp;nbsp;necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am thinking of trying Go, but I will leave that for later because I don&amp;#8217;t really want to bite off more than I can chew. Which I am already doing,&amp;nbsp;anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Closing&amp;nbsp;thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been using this setup for a few months now and I am very satisfied with my decision. My Linux desktop is fast and sleek with a good-looking interface, and installing stuff is as easy as writing one shell command. I can definitely see why many developers use Linux, and I will probably make a full switch from Windows when&amp;nbsp;possible.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="linux"></category><category term="linux"></category><category term="learning"></category></entry></feed>