<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Alex Gonzalez - power bi, data viz</title><link href="https://alexgonzalezc.dev/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://alexgonzalezc.dev/feeds/power-bi-data-viz.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://alexgonzalezc.dev/</id><updated>2019-12-06T17:42:00+01:00</updated><subtitle>Hey! I'm Alex, a developer specialising on data engineering, machine learning, data science, visualization and analytics.</subtitle><entry><title>An introduction to Power BI for data scientists</title><link href="https://alexgonzalezc.dev/posts/introduction-to-power-bi-for-data-scientists.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-12-06T17:42:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-12-06T17:42:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Alex Gonzalez</name></author><id>tag:alexgonzalezc.dev,2019-12-06:/posts/introduction-to-power-bi-for-data-scientists.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Power &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BI&lt;/span&gt; is a great free tool that can be used to quickly prototype visualizations for exploratory data&amp;nbsp;analysis.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Get started with Power &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BI&lt;/span&gt; to speed up your exploratory data analysis when looking for trends and features than might be useful for prediction or classification with machine learning&amp;nbsp;algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Getting&amp;nbsp;Data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Connecting to a data source in Power &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BI&lt;/span&gt; is quite straightforward. Just navigate to the Home tab in the ribbon and select &lt;strong&gt;Get Data&lt;/strong&gt; to find a dropdown menu of possible options. Common sources are &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SQL&lt;/span&gt; Server, Analysis Services (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;SSAS&lt;/span&gt;), Excel and Dynamics 365, among others. In most cases, such as &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SQL&lt;/span&gt; Server, you can also specify the query you want to run against the database.
Note that when connecting to a source you can either query the data directly through &lt;strong&gt;DirectQuery&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;Import&lt;/strong&gt; modes, but you cannot combine both methods into the same solution. There is also the &lt;strong&gt;LiveConnection&lt;/strong&gt; mode, a variation of DirectQuery geared towards &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SSAS&lt;/span&gt; Tabular that we will not cover&amp;nbsp;here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are some crucial differences between the two connection modes:
* In DirectQuery, the data stays at the source and is not imported into your machine&amp;#8217;s memory and the size of the &lt;code&gt;.pbix&lt;/code&gt; file is dramatically lower than an import solution. However, each event during report visualization will trigger live queries that might harm the user experience. 
* In Import mode, the data model is loaded into Power &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BI&lt;/span&gt; desktop and remains static until a refresh is triggered. This makes for smooth user experience but increase file size and memory&amp;nbsp;consumption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you have selected the source, Power &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BI&lt;/span&gt; will present you with a preview of your data. If everything looks &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OK&lt;/span&gt;, you can continue towards the next step. Otherwise, you can review your query and make any necessary&amp;nbsp;changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also use a folder as your source, allowing you to import several files at once such as a series of Excel or &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CSV&lt;/span&gt; files. They are loaded as binary data types and double clicking them loads their&amp;nbsp;values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Clean and&amp;nbsp;Transform&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Data&amp;nbsp;Modeling&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There some key aspects to take into account when modeling data with Power &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BI&lt;/span&gt;, such as data categories and summarization; or establishing adequate relationships among your tables. You can also create custom hierarchies such as Year/Month/Week or Country/Destination/Region by dragging dragging columns on top of each other in the Report or Data&amp;nbsp;View.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Data types, categories and format&amp;nbsp;strings&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are several different types of data to work with in Power &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BI&lt;/span&gt;, such as integer, decimal/fixed, currency, date/time/datetime, string and binary objects.
The data type is what allows certain functions and operations to be performed on a specific column, and it&amp;#8217;s &lt;strong&gt;not the same as the data format&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The format string is the way that this data will be visually represented, such as percentage, with thousand separator, with decimals&amp;#8230; There also many different formats for date and time objects which can also be changed flexibly with the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DAX&lt;/span&gt; &lt;code&gt;FORMAT ( )&lt;/code&gt; function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Text data can be categorized, which is useful when you have geographical data or URLs in your table. Setting a data category for these columns allows for advanced features such as &lt;span class="caps"&gt;URL&lt;/span&gt; icons, embedded images and map visuals. Numerical data is uncategorized by default, since we use data types to differentiate it.
Both types of data need &lt;em&gt;summarization&lt;/em&gt;, which is the default statistic that will be calculated by visuals using the measure. Possible options are &lt;code&gt;sum&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;average&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;minimum&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;maximum&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;count&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;distinct&lt;/code&gt; for numerical types, while text types only have count and distinct. You can also use &lt;code&gt;first&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;last&lt;/code&gt; within some&amp;nbsp;visuals. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s important to make a distinction between modeling your data within the Power Query editor or within Power &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BI&lt;/span&gt; Desktop itself, since different operations can be performed and the computational load is different. Usually, we use the &lt;em&gt;Query Editor&lt;/em&gt; to clean, shape and transform data from the source, while the &lt;em&gt;Data View&lt;/em&gt; (i.e. Power Pivot) is often used to model the imported data and define calculations for&amp;nbsp;analytics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Power Query editor and the &lt;code&gt;M&lt;/code&gt; language&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Power Query is a data discovery and query tool, good for shaping and mashing up data even before you’ve added the first row of data to the table. Inside the Power Query editor you can use the &lt;code&gt;M&lt;/code&gt; programming language to shape your data, creating step by step scripts that iteratively clean, transform and add columns to your model.
Moreover, you can leverage the amazing Power &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BI&lt;/span&gt; user interface that makes this data engineering process very straight-forward and with zero necessary knowledge of &lt;code&gt;M&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the operations you can perform&amp;nbsp;are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Duplicate, transform or split&amp;nbsp;columns&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can use regular expressions, functions and calculations to engineer new&amp;nbsp;features.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Change data types and&amp;nbsp;formats&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Power Query can also detect automatically the best data type for your column if you are not&amp;nbsp;sure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pivot, unpivot and sort&amp;nbsp;columns&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Merge (join) and append (union)&amp;nbsp;queries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove or keep duplicates, errors, nulls,&amp;nbsp;headers&amp;#8230;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Group by columns and aggregate&amp;nbsp;measures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Enhance your model with the Data&amp;nbsp;View&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only can you explore all of your data interactively within this view, but you can also further improve the analytical capabilities of your model by using &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DAX&lt;/span&gt; expressions that leverage different filtering contexts and time frames to create complex&amp;nbsp;features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Create calculated&amp;nbsp;columns&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can create calculated columns, for example, to establish a relationship between different tables, or to create indexes that could later be used as reference by iterator functions.
Creating a calculated column consumes memory in your machine as it expands your data model if your tables have many records. Consider creating them only when necessary or for extremely complex calculations that should be run&amp;nbsp;live.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember to custom sort your columns, i.e. &lt;code&gt;MonthName&lt;/code&gt; should be sorted by &lt;code&gt;MonthNumber&lt;/code&gt; and not alphabetically by&amp;nbsp;itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Create calculated&amp;nbsp;measures&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Measures are calculations that exists in your Power &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BI&lt;/span&gt; data model and is computed on the fly at each event. With &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DAX&lt;/span&gt; you can define a measure once and then slice it by all the different fields in your model, as long as the necessary relationships&amp;nbsp;exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since they are computed at query time, calculated measures consume more &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CPU&lt;/span&gt; than a column, but they do not grow the tables in your data&amp;nbsp;model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Create calculated&amp;nbsp;tables&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Calculated tables allow you to express a whole new range of modeling capabilities, such as performing different types of joins and creating new tables on the fly based on the results of a formula.
For example, you can create a date dimension with &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DAX&lt;/span&gt; by using the date to derive all necessary attributes such as month, week number or day of the week, or create summary tables with aggregated&amp;nbsp;values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Relationships in the data&amp;nbsp;model&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data relationships are similar to how a cube is structured in Analysis Services. In the Model View you can access a diagrammatic view of your data, and you can define how your tables are related.
To create a relationship, just click on a column on your fact table and drag it into the key on the dimension table. This generates an arrow indicating the active relationship, which you can double click to access advanced options such as setting the cardinality or the direction of the&amp;nbsp;relationship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your options for cardinality are Many to One, and One to One. Many to One is the fact to dimension type relationship, for example a sales table with multiple rows per product being matched up with a table listing products in their own unique&amp;nbsp;row.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Visualization and report&amp;nbsp;design&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Visuals are the main element of Power &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BI&lt;/span&gt; reporting, and they have a wide range of formatting options that allows for almost limitless&amp;nbsp;customization. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Editing&amp;nbsp;interactions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you have multiple visualizations on the same report page, selecting a particular segment by clicking or using a slicer will affect all the visuals on that page. In some cases, though, you may want to slice only specific visuals. For example, you might not want a scatter plot to be cross-filtered because that would remove crucial meaning from the visualization.
You can define how visuals interacts with each other when the user selects data&amp;nbsp;points. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Z-order&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you have lots of elements on a report, Power &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BI&lt;/span&gt; lets you manage how they overlap with each other. How items are layered, or arranged on top of one another, is often referred to as the z-order.
This is particularly useful when you want to use shapes to create backgrounds, highlights or containers. For example, you might use a shape to create the background for your report title, or to enclose a set of KPIs in a container. You can also set a semi-transparent shape over a graph section to highlight&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Bookmarks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bookmarks are a great feature that allow for some nice tricks with user interaction. Essentially, a bookmark is a snapshot of your report page at a given time. They can save filter state, formatting options, visual placement, etc.
You can use them to change between report pages, create a guided navigation for the user, change themes, show help or filter panes, send emails and many more&amp;nbsp;things. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Time&amp;nbsp;Intelligence&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time intelligence manages complex time-based calculations with reduced user input. It needs a date table with no date gaps, which Power &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BI&lt;/span&gt; creates automagically if the setting &lt;code&gt;Auto Date/Time&lt;/code&gt; is enabled, which is the default case.
It is recommended to create your own date table instead of relying on this one, since it&amp;#8217;s not possible to adjust if necessary and can actually only be viewed from &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DAX&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;Studio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you decide to work with it, you can use dot notation to access the time calculations, i.e. &lt;code&gt;Orders[Date].[Year]&lt;/code&gt; to automatically extract the year of that&amp;nbsp;date.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="power bi, data viz"></category><category term="data science"></category></entry></feed>